本字幕由 YYeTs人人影视 原创翻译制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新 请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
■
翻译    婷宝
Translator  ChampionT
翻译     紫杉
Translator  Zishan_stone
翻译   板凳小早
Translator      L.N
翻译    句号
Translator  Johanna
时间轴  艾田
Timer      Landy
时间轴  大米饭
Timer        Liko
校对  半糖
Editor   Angelia
后期  鱼骨头
Encoder   Fishbone
总监  猫家小丢
Leader    Adam.Diu
特别感谢  小石头
Special Thanks   Sienna
人类星球
第七集
只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落都留下了印迹
in every habitat on Earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world,
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
we still use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
人类总是被河流所吸引
Humans have always been drawn to rivers.
河流流经地球上每个角落
Rivers flow through every environment,
带给我们生命之源
bringing us the essentials of life-
淡水
fresh water,
食物
food,
以及便利的交通
and ready-made highways.
然而  水可载舟
But what rivers give,
亦可覆舟
they can also take away.
可以形成洪水
They can flood,
冰冻
freeze
甚至干涸  消失殆尽
and sometimes disappear altogether.
河流令我们承载了巨大的风险
Rivers force us to take great risks.
接下来将为您呈现非同一般的
These are remarkable stories of survival
在意想不到之处求生的精彩片段
from the most unpredictable habitat of them all.
河流
亦敌亦友
现在正值季风时节
It's the monsoon season,
东南亚最大的河流  湄公河蓄水充足
and the mighty Mekong, southeast Asia's greatest river, is in full flood.
位于柬埔寨和老挝之间的湄公河
Between Cambodia and Laos,
此时湍流之宽  乃是世界之最
the Mekong current creates the widest rapids in the world.
孔恩瀑布是捕鱼的最佳去处
The Khone Falls are great for fishing,
但也十分危险
but also very dangerous,
当地渔民山酿对此再清楚不过了
as Sam Niang, a local fisherman, knows all too well.
渔网非常危险
如果我撒的不对  就会丧命
恐怕河水会把我卷走
那时谁也没有办法救我
迁徙的鱼群被困在这里
Migrating fish get trapped here,
等待时机穿越激流
waiting to get up the rapids.
山酿不得不冒着生命危险捕获这些鱼
Sam Niang has to risk his life to catch them.
他有一家七口需要养活
He has a family of seven to feed.
他从家附近的河岸上开始
He starts by fishing from the riverside, near his home.
季风时节
During the monsoon,
湄公河的水量暴增至平时的二十倍
the Mekong swells to 20 times its normal volume,
这带来更多的鱼群
which brings more fish,
但也给捕鱼增加了很大的难度
but makes them much harder to catch.
雨过之后  我担心会从岩石上滑下
石头上覆盖着黏液
走的时候必须十分小心
一个早晨过去了  他的渔网依然空空如也
After a morning, his net is still empty.
还有另外一个选择
There is another option-
那就是在湍流中最为猛烈之处的一个孤岛
an island out in the main rapids.
要想到达那里  山酿就得冒上生命危险
But to get there, Sam Niang must take his life into his hands.
在旱季  他用旧电缆和少许绳索
In the dry season, he built a high wire across the rapids
造了一架穿越激流的绳索桥
out of old cable and bits of rope.
踩在绳索上时必须万分小心
如果滑倒  我必死无疑
而我不想扔下我的孩子们
一年中的这个时段
At this time of the year,
这里激流的流量约是尼亚加拉瀑布的两倍
these rapids have nearly twice the flow of Niagara Falls-
每秒逾一千一百万升
more than 11 million litres a second.
他终于到达了他所中意的捕鱼地点
He makes it to his favourite fishing perch.
汹涌的湍流将鱼赶入网中
Turbulent currents corral the fish,
山酿很快为家人捕获到了晚餐
and Sam Niang soon lands his family's supper.
尽管这里鱼量充足
Though the fish are plentiful here,
但他每次只能带几公斤回家
the most he can carry back is a few kilos at a time.
负重过大会让他在绳索上失去平衡
Any more, and he might lose his balance.
今天  山酿战胜了湄公河
Today, Sam Niang won his battle with the Mekong.
而明天  为了养活他的家人
Tomorrow, to keep his family fed,
他还要继续战斗
he'll have to fight it again.
河流之所以危险  不仅仅在于水的力量
It's not just the power of water that makes rivers dangerous.
也在于其神秘莫测的本性
It's their erratic nature too.
准确解读河流的情况
Reading a river correctly
意味着生死一线的转机
can mean the difference between life and death.
詹斯卡尔峡谷是西藏边缘的一个神秘世界
The Zanskar valley is a hidden world on the edge of Tibet,
就在喜马拉雅山的中心地带
in the heart of the Himalayas.
冬天  这里被冰雪覆盖
In winter, it's cut off by snow.
进出之路尽被阻隔
All roads in and out are impassable.
斯坦金要送他的两个孩子去学校
Stanzin needs to get his two children to school,
但最近的学校也在一百公里之外
but the nearest school is 100 kilometres away,
唯一的路径
and the only way to get there
便是一条冰冻之河
is to walk down a frozen river.
需要六天的艰苦跋涉  这条路因极其危险
It's a six-day trek, so dangerous it's got its own name-
而获名"大披巾"  冰雪之毯之意
the Chadar- the blanket of ice.
要通过此路  必须经过严寒
They'll have to brave sub-zero temperatures,
雪崩和刺骨冰水的考验
avalanches and freezing water.
这学期在一周后开始
Term starts in a week.
上学的时间到了
It's time for the school run,
对十一岁的多卡来说  这是一次艰难的旅途
a formidable trip for 11-year-old Dolkar.
多卡  天空晴朗  正是出发的好时候
多卡十四岁的哥哥丘星也会同去
Dolkar's 14-year-old brother, Chosing, is coming too.
家人提前就为这次旅行做好了准备
The family prepare for the journey ahead.
多卡  东西都准备好了吗
好了
母亲为他们织了
Their mother has knitted
厚厚的羊毛袜来御寒
them thick woollen socks to protect them.
袜子合脚吗
千万要小心  多卡
别怕"大披巾"
你会害怕吗
不  和你在一起就不怕
这对兄妹相信他们父亲的
The brother and sister depend on
勇气和生存技能
their father's courage and skill.
好好学习
好好照顾自己  宝贝
这一定是全世界最危险的求学之路
This has to be the most perilous school run in the world.
好好照顾自己  别着凉
多卡  丘星  保重
春天的融化似乎来得过早些
The spring melt seems to have started early,
这令斯坦金甚为担心
which worries Stanzin.
这路会很难走
但我们必须去学校
除了"大披巾"  我们别无选择
我要带着孩子们去上学
来吧  别怕
斯坦金要确保冰能承受他们的重量
Stanzin has to make sure the ice can take their weight.
我在检查冰层的时候  感觉手的震动
就能分辨出冰层是否能承载我们的重量
他的这个技能马上就被验证了
And his expertise is tested immediately.
跟着我
一直跟着我
危险并不只在脚下
The danger is not only underfoot.
另一威胁是雪崩
There's another threat- avalanches.
怎么会有雪崩呢
雪太多了
我们得走另一条路
七天前  有人就死于詹斯卡尔河的雪崩
Seven days ago, an avalanche killed a man on the Zanskar river.
强烈的春日阳光带来另一个问题
The unusual spring sunshine has brought another problem.
流动的河水使得冰层开始融化
The river's current has already melted the ice.
斯坦金必须想办法通过眼前的障碍
Stanzin has to find a way past the barrier.
要么走这边  要么走那边  你们在这里等
这附近唯一一条路是一段狭窄的岩壁
The only way around is a narrow ledge.
过来  我们能走过去
这岩壁仅二十厘米宽  并被冰雪覆盖
The ledge is barely 20 centimetres wide and covered with snow.
与下面冻结的河流相距十米
There's a ten-metre drop to the freezing river below.
岩壁的末端有一些金属桩用以攀爬
The ledge ends with some metal pegs to climb down.
丘星爬过去了
Chosing makes it.
现在轮到多卡了
Now it's Dolkar's turn.
过来  多卡
过来  慢点儿  慢点儿
把你的手给我
脚踩在那儿
另一只脚也放下来
顺着岩石爬
我很害怕
过来
我把脚踩在这儿吗
是  抓住铁桩
他们不能耽搁
They mustn't delay.
夜幕即将降临
Night is falling fast,
温度会骤降至零下三十摄氏度
and the temperature will plummet to minus 30 Celsius.
幸运的是  斯坦金知道附近有个山洞
Luckily, Stanzin knows a cave nearby.
你的手套干了吗
没事儿吧
-没事  -把袜子穿上
把这个戴上  不然会冷
孩子们需要睡觉
The children need their sleep.
前面还有"大披巾"最为危险的路段要走
The most dangerous part of the Chadar is still ahead.
一路上并不总是艰难险境
It's not all hard slog.
但是多卡的兴奋劲儿并没有持续多久
But Dolkar's fun can't last.
她的年龄最小  也是最先感到寒冷难耐的
As the smallest, she's the first to feel the cold.
她开始跟不上步伐了
She starts to lag behind.
在地球最高的山脉之中
One little girl on a melting ice river,
一个小女孩蹒跚于正在融化的冰河之上
among the greatest mountains on Earth.
终于到了最后一程
Now for the final leg.
如果掉进河里  你只能活八分钟
别走在我前面  你可能会掉下去
好的
冰川融化得只剩薄薄一层了
The melting ice has left just a tiny shelf.
在这里等
我先过去看看
冰层非常薄
It's thin.
斯坦金担心它承受不了他们的重量
Stanzin is worried it won't take their weight.
随着他匍匐前进  冰层开始劈啪作响
As he advances, the ice starts to crack.
我害怕
斯坦金的重量使得冰块又脆弱了几分
With the ice weakened by Stanzin's weight,
孩子们必须鼓起勇气独立面对
the children have to brave it on their own.
-多卡先来  -好
慢点儿  爬过来
靠里些
慢一点
这里很薄  可能会裂开
小心点
多卡成功了  现在轮到丘星
Dolkar's made it, now for Chosing.
这里很薄  要小心
父亲的生存技能
Thanks to their dad's expertise,
保证了孩子们平安穿越"大披巾"
the children have survived the Chadar.
在冰河上挺过了六天
Six days out on the ice river.
喜马拉雅山的列城
The Himalayan town of Leh,
是孩子们旅途的终点
journey's end for the children.
他们直奔学校
They rush straight to the school.
正好还有充分的时间告别
There's just enough time for a goodbye.
好好学习
爸爸  保重
我会给你打电话
给你寄钱过来
好好学习  知道吗
斯坦金现在要独自一人踏上归途
Stanzin now faces the return journey on his own.
消融中的冰河不仅仅
Melting river ice doesn't just
令长途跋涉变得更加艰难
make travelling harder.
当结冰的河面开始融化时
When frozen rivers break up,
数以吨计的冰块四处漂浮
tonnes of ice start to flow,
成为巨大隐患
a potential disaster,
即便是现代城市中心都受到威胁
even in the heart of a modern city.
在加拿大首都渥太华
In the Canadian capital, Ottawa,
春季冰河的融解
spring melt turns the Rideau river
使丽都河成为全民头号公敌
into public enemy number one.
最危险的地方在于
The danger point is
冰冻的瀑布之上还有一架人行天桥
a footbridge on a frozen waterfall,
而这瀑布正是丽都河
a bottleneck where the Rideau
汇入渥太华河的瓶颈河段
flows into the Ottawa river.
现在是二月末
It's late February,
这里的冰层正在融化
and the ice is melting here too.
巨大的冰块会形成一座危险的大坝
Ice blocks are in danger of forming a dam,
可能会引发破坏极大的洪涝灾害
which might lead to devastating flooding.
这样的自然威胁需要人们果敢地介入干预
A natural threat that needs a daring human solution.
有请"冰坝终结者"
Meet the ice-dam busters!
他们不仅要预测大自然的举动
Their job isn't just to predict nature,
还必须战胜大自然
they have to beat it!
天桥后有数以千吨的
There are thousands of tonnes of ice behind the bridge,
厚达一米的冰层
up to a metre thick.
这支队伍要破坏冰层
The team needs to break it up
以保证河水的正常流动
to keep the river flowing.
第一步
Stage one-
将冰层切割成长条状
cut the ice into long strips.
但体积还是太大  无法穿过天桥
They're still too large to flow under the bridge,
所以  进行第二步
so, for stage two,
采用了更为可靠的做法
the team uses a more persuasive force...
准备
Now!
安放数百公斤的炸药
...hundreds of kilos of dynamite.
开始
Hup!
现在  小块的冰可以顺利通过天桥
Bite-size pieces now flow easily under the bridge
越过瀑布了
and over the falls.
渥太华市中心又能平安度过一年
The centre of Ottawa is safe for another year.
世界上最大的河流
The world's largest rivers
给我们的生活带来最大的危险
bring the most danger to our lives.
它们的洪流可是致命的
Their floods can be devastating.
泛滥之初总是毫无征兆
They often happen without warning,
而我们除了仓皇出逃别无它法
and there's nothing we can do but try to escape.
在孟加拉  数千万的人口
In Bangladesh, tens of millions of people
不得不在恒河及其支流冲击河岸时
can be displaced when the Ganges and her tributaries
举家迁移
burst their banks.
河流的力量非常强大
The river is so strong,
它经常会改变河道方向
it regularly changes course,
同时冲刷着沿岸的陆地
brushing land aside as it goes.
一个月前穆罕默德・贾里尔的村庄
A month ago, Mohamed Jaleel's village
离河岸还有一百多米远
was 100 metres from the bank.
今天他的房子就面临着被冲走的危险
Today, his house is about to be swept away.
他和邻居们
He and his neighbours have
只有几分钟的时间搬家
only minutes to move his home.
而其余的居民只能在旁无助地看着
The rest of the villagers look on, helpless,
越涨越高的河水吞噬着他们的家园
as the rising river obliterates their land.
在南美洲  洪水的力量强大到
In South America, floods can be so huge
人们不得不用全年的时间
that the entire year has to
作出防洪计划
be spent planning for them.
在亚马逊盆地
In the Amazon basin,
一位母亲为上涨的河水做着万全的准备
one mother prepares for the rising waters.
贾妮娅生活在巴西的尼格罗河
Jarnia lives by the Rio Negro in Brazil.
现在是十一月份  正值旱季
It's November, the dry season,
是食物最丰盛的季节
the time of plenty.
不仅能够轻松捕到鱼
Fish are so easy to catch,
她甚至还有多余的食物喂食当地的江豚
she even has enough to feed the local river dolphins.
来吧
过来吃鱼
但是六个月后涨潮之时
But in six months' time, when the flood water invades,
这些江豚  还有小鱼
all these dolphins and the fish with them
都会藏匿在洪溢林中完成生育大计
will disappear into the flooded forest to breed.
如果没有了鱼
When the fish are gone,
养活这一大家子就是个梦魇了
feeding her large family will become a nightmare.
要熬过这段时间就必须未雨绸缪
Surviving such hard times means thinking ahead,
贾妮娅为此制定了四步计划
and Jarnia has a four-stage plan.
第一步  提前六个月
Stage one is collecting turtle eggs
在涨潮之前采集乌龟蛋
six months before the floods arrive.
这里有痕迹
我找到了两个巢
旱季时河龟会在滩涂上
River turtles lay thousands of eggs
产下数千枚蛋
in the dry season beaches,
以待孵育
which they leave to hatch.
河水上涨时
Turtles are a reliable source of protein
乌龟是最稳定的蛋白质来源
when the waters rise,
所以这些蛋就很珍贵了
so these eggs are precious.
回到村庄  开始第二步
Back in the village, it's time for stage two.
贾妮娅把蛋重新埋在自己的小龟苗圃里
Jarnia reburies the eggs in her turtle nursery.
在野外  很多龟蛋会被动物吃掉
In the wild, many eggs would be eaten by animals,
但在这里  它们是安全的
but here they'll be safe.
四个月后  到了三月
By March, four months later,
三千多只小龟破壳而出
3,000 eggs have hatched.
于是开始第三步
It's stage three-
放生
release day!
我们很喜欢这些小龟
把它们放回河里
我们真的很开心
一旦有小龟不幸死了  我们会很难过
是时候将小宝贝们送走了
It's time to release the babies.
不过会有足够的乌龟活下来
But will enough of them survive
在涨潮之际为全村提供食物吗
to feed the village in the floods to come?
现在是六月  大雨滂沱
It's June, the height of the rains.
水位上升了七米
The river rises seven metres.
贾妮娅的村落完全变了样
Jarnia's village is transformed.
树林被水淹没
The forest is flooded,
最近的陆地
and the nearest dry land
也要六个多小时的水路才能到达
is more than six hours' rowing away.
贾妮娅一家现在正被地球上
Jarnia's family is now marooned
规模最大的季节性洪水困得动弹不得
by the greatest annual flood on the planet.
到最后一步计划了
Time for the final stage.
贾妮娅和她的妹妹多拉准备出门猎龟
Jarnia and her sister Dora prepare to go turtle-hunting.
贾妮娅的丈夫弗朗西斯科
Jarnia's husband, Francisco,
为她们做了一支猎龟的长矛
makes them a turtle-hunting spear,
姐妹俩出发觅食去了
and then the two sisters set off in search of food.
她们之前的辛勤劳作
Will their hard work
能换回餐桌上的累累硕果吗
bring dinner to the table?
起初  形势并不乐观
At first, it's not looking promising.
它们不上钩
是啊  根本不上钩
今天很难能捕到龟了
但是贾妮娅发现了一只
Then Jarnia spots one.
抓到一只
今天能吃顿好饭了
她的准备工作获得了回报
Her preparation's paid off.
家里人不会饿肚子了
She'll be able to feed everyone.
贾妮娅的远见卓识
Jarnia's foresight has pulled
令她的家人度过了这段艰难的洪水时期
her family through another difficult flood.
河流中的一些生物对人类有着直接的威胁
Some river creatures pose a direct threat to humans.
位于非洲的赞比西河
The Zambezi river in Africa
生活着如大象  鳄鱼和河马这样
is used by elephants, crocodiles and hippos,
陆地上最为危险的动物
some of the continent's most dangerous animals.
渔民约瑟法特和他的兄弟们找到一个
Fisherman Josphat and his brothers have found a safe,
有些骇人但还算安全的捕鱼地点
if slightly hair-raising, fishing spot,
在这里不但可以捕获食物
a place where they can catch lunch
而且不会有生命危险
without becoming dinner themselves.
我们步行前往这条河
要走六英里
这里水流湍急  所以不会有鳄鱼出没
鳄鱼和河马害怕急流
他们要去的地方也许可以避开鳄鱼
The place they're heading for may be safe from crocodiles,
但危险依然存在
but it does have a drawback.
我们从来不单独行动
总是结伴而行
捕鱼时即便出现状况
我们也不分开
约瑟法特的捕鱼地点之所以危险
The reason Josphat's fishing pools are far from safe
是因为他们所处的位置
is their precarious position,
正是维多利亚瀑布的最顶端
at the very top of Victoria Falls.
我们从不害怕
祖辈教过我们该去何方
约瑟法特的勇敢与技巧
Josphat's bravery and skill
让他能够到其他动物无法涉足的地方捕鱼
enable him to fish where no animal dares to venture.
人们能够克服洪水
People can overcome floods
甚至学会在巨大瀑布的边缘捕鱼
and even learn to fish on giant waterfalls,
但在河流的另外一面
but there's one face of a river
才真正令人难以生存
that's virtually impossible to survive.
当河流干涸并消失
When a river dries up and disappears,
所有生命亦随之逝去
all life drains away.
利马盖是肯尼亚北部的一个桑布鲁骆驼牧人
Lemagas is a Samburu camel herder in northern Kenya.
八个月来这里没有下过一滴雨
No rain has fallen here for eight months.
今年旱情极其严重
It's a severe drought,
米尔吉斯河早已消失
and the Milgis river has vanished.
利马盖不得不带领着他宝贵的骆驼群
Lemagas has been forced to range deep into the desert,
深入沙漠寻找食物
searching for fresh food for his precious camels.
现在他们远离家园
Now they are far away from home,
而且饮用水早已耗尽
and they've run out of drinking water.
对我们桑布鲁人来说  水是最珍贵的东西
每当旱季来临时
我们都祈求自然之神赐予我们雨水
甚至连骆驼都无法忍受
Not even the camels can survive
如此长时间水分的匮乏
this long without a drink.
利马盖知道这里有水
Lemagas knows there is water here,
就藏在这河床之下
hidden underneath the river bed.
但是如何去寻找呢
But how can he find it?
桑布鲁人学会了依靠另一种游牧的动物
The Samburu have learned to rely on another nomadic creature,
它们总是在夜间出没
one that usually travels at night.
在利马盖和他的骆驼休息之时
While Lemagas and his camels rest,
不远处  一些体型庞大的水源占卜师
not far away, some giant water-diviners
在河床上嗅来嗅去
are sniffing out the river bed.
大象鼻子的灵敏度
An elephant's trunk- its nose-
远远超过人类
is far more sensitive than a human's,
这意味着它们可以找到
which means it can tell
何处的水源离地表更近
where the water table is closest to the surface.
一头大象每天要喝掉一百升的水
Elephants must drink 100 litres a day
它的鼻子每次能吸入八升水
and can suck up eight litres of water at a time.
喝足以后  象群在黎明到来之前就离开了
Having drunk, the elephants leave before dawn.
第二天一早
Early next morning,
利马盖和他的骆驼们尾随象群的足迹
Lemagas and his camels are on the elephants'trail.
大象帮了我们大忙
寻找水源的路上  它们会留下粪便
我们随着粪便一路走下去
就能找到水源
它们走到哪里  哪里就有水
大象们真棒
带我们找到了这个水洼
如果你懂得如何寻找的话
Even a dry river bed holds water
即便是干涸的河床依然饱含水分
if you know where to look.
他们唱起颂歌感谢上帝  还有大象们
They sing their thanks to the gods, and the elephants.
几天以后
A few days later,
利马盖终于回到他的村庄
Lemagas finally returns to his village
带着他的永恒之井
with its permanent deep well.
他始终记得在荒野中得到的帮助
He doesn't forget the help he's been given in the wild.
归来后的头等大事就是取出弥足珍贵的水
The first thing he does is to bring up precious water,
不单单为了他的族人和家人
not just for his herd and his family,
当然还有他的动物朋友们
but for his wild friends too.
我们把水放在外面
给路过的动物们喝
因为我们桑布鲁人
崇尚与万物共生存
他从未忘记夜行水源占卜师的恩情
He doesn't forget his nocturnal water-diviners,
若没有它们
for without them,
利马盖和他的骆驼群在远离家园的地方
Lemagas and his camels could never survive
势必难以存活
when they're far away from home.
远在四千公里外的马里
Over 4,000 kilometres away, in Mali, another dry river,
尼日尔河的一条支流几近干涸
a tributary of the Niger,
一个人正面临艰难的抉择
is forcing one man into making a difficult decision.
他叫乌瑟曼
His name is Ouseman,
他是杰内古城的泥瓦匠专家
and he's a master mason in Djenne,
这座古城所有建筑均由河泥建成
an ancient city made entirely of river mud.
他的工作就是维护城中的清真寺
His job is to maintain the city's mosque,
这是世界上最大最早的泥制建筑
the biggest and oldest mud building in the world.
清真寺是乌瑟曼族人最为重要的部分
It's the heart of Ouseman's culture.
伊斯兰教对我们来说至关重要
我们的清真寺举世无双
乌瑟曼的烦恼在于
Ouseman's problem is this-
每年雨季到来之前
every year the mosque needs
必须给清真寺涂上一层新的河泥来保护它
a fresh coat of mud to protect it before the rains arrive.
在干涸的河床上
Down in the dry river bed,
人们将泥与米糠混合
the mud is blended with rice husks,
然后令其发酵
and then left to ferment.
但是今年的发酵物没有达到适当的粘稠度
But this year, the mix hasn't reached the right consistency,
而大雨将至
and now the rains are almost upon him.
沙尘暴正在肆虐
Dust storms are blowing in,
这是雨季开始的前兆
the first signs that the wet season is about to begin.
这座神圣的寺庙急缺一件新的"雨衣"
The sacred building desperately needs a new storm-proof skin.
两天后
Two days later,
乌瑟曼和他的朋友易卜拉欣又来到河边
Ouseman and his friend Ibrahim return to the river.
可以给寺庙涂上新泥了吗
今天看来可以了
这是个重大决定
It's a big decision.
消息不胫而走  全城集体出动
Word spreads fast, and everyone comes down to help.
杰内古城的人民
Everyone in Djenne has been waiting
每天都盼着这个特殊的日子
all year for this special day.
嵌于其中的棕榈木板成为泥瓦匠的踏板
The built-in palm logs are perches for the plasterers.
人们倾巢而出  为保卫清真寺贡献一份力量
The whole town mucks in to protect the mosque for another year.
人们如此积极只为一个理由
愿自己的祷告能够得到神的回应
杰内古城的清真寺已有七百年的历史
There's been a mud mosque in Djenne for 700 years,
这个神圣的一城中心因河泥而兴旺着
the sacred heart of a city fashioned from river mud.
我们与河流的关系纷纭复杂
Our relationship with rivers is never easy.
所谓水可载舟
Their waters can give us so much
亦可覆舟
but can also take everything away.
我们总是被河流狂放
We will always be at the mercy of their wild
而且捉摸不定的姿态所支配
and unpredictable nature.
但有一个民族已经学会
But one culture has found an inspiring way
与暴虐的河流和平共处
of mastering their savage rivers.
在印度东北部
In northeast India,
一个神秘世界隐藏在悬崖峭壁之间
a giant cliff leads up into a hidden world,
那就是梅加拉亚邦
Meghalaya.
位于海拔两千米的山峦之中
Nearly two kilometres high
季风性积雨云萦绕其间
and buffeted by monsoon storm clouds,
这里很可能是世界上最为潮湿的地方
this is possibly the wettest place on Earth.
降雨量在一年之内一度达到二十五米
Once, 25 metres of rain fell here in a year,
创造了世界纪录
the world record.
在这里生活面临着巨大的考验
Living here poses an unusual problem,
这不仅仅是避雨的问题
and it's not just keeping dry.
几乎所有降水都发生在夏季季风时节
Nearly all the rain falls during the summer monsoon.
涓涓细流摇身一变  成为滔滔山洪
Rivers switch from gentle streams to raging torrents.
河水肆虐且难以捉摸
They become wild and unpredictable
几乎无法渡过
and almost impossible to cross.
哈利和他的侄女朱莉安娜
Harley and his niece Juliana
正忙着进行一项巧妙的解决方案
are busy cultivating a cunning solution.
看这儿  看这儿
我教你怎么做
三十年前  哈利在这片河岸
30 years ago, Harley planted this strangler fig
种下了这棵勒颈无花果树
on the river's edge,
今天  他教朱莉安娜如何养护
and today, he's teaching Juliana how to care for it.
盘根错节的无花果树根
The fig's tangled roots
保护着河岸的土不被冲走
help to prevent the bank being washed away.
你要小心照看这些树根
确保它们不被破坏
他教朱莉安娜慢慢地将树根穿过
He teaches Juliana to coax the roots across
现在还只是条小溪的河
what is now just a stream.
当树根到达另一端  他们将其固定好
When they reach the other side, they'll take hold there.
这是抵御洪水的基本结构
This is the basis of a structure that will survive any deluge.
一座生命之桥
A living bridge.
这项工程浩大
It's an epic project that
没人能单靠自己的一生就完成
no man can complete in one lifetime,
所以哈利向朱莉安娜传授知识
so Harley is passing on his knowledge to Juliana.
注意这里  我会告诉你怎么做
这么做对吗
朱莉安娜每年都得来打理这些树根
Each year,Juliana will need to tend the roots,
让它们更加粗壮
making them stronger.
如果她在有生之年完成了她的桥
If she stays and completes her bridge,
这里将成为村民们往来通道的一部分
it will become part of the commuter route here,
由许多生命之桥构成的交通网络
a network of dozens of living bridges
连通着梅加拉亚邦的山谷
that connect the valleys of Meghalaya.
有些这样的桥已经有几百年的历史了
Some of them are many centuries old.
甚至还有些是双层的
There are even double-deckers.
这座桥可以一直生长五百年
你的孩子们会用上它
以及你孩子的孩子
有了朱莉安娜的照料
With Juliana to look after it,
这座桥的未来令人充满希望
the future of this young bridge looks secure,
它会成为扎实稳固  生命力十足的建筑
sustainable, living architecture
并伴随着人们一代又一代的成长
that will live and grow for generations,
这是全世界甚为罕见的景象
one of the very few examples in the world
人类发明了这种奏效且天然的解决方案
where humans have come up with a successful and natural solution,
通过与大自然的协作
a way of working with nature
来克服自然河流造成的难题
to overcome the problems a wild river can cause.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
人类星球河流摄制组的工作人员
For the Human Planet Rivers team,
在汹涌澎湃的湄公河上进行拍摄
filming on the Mekong river at the height of the monsoon
遇到了许多挑战
raised many challenges.
重要的是  如何捕捉到
Mainly, how do you capture
一个精彩绝伦的镜头  而不让你的摄像机
a remarkable event without losing your camera,
小组成员或者你追拍的渔夫
your crew or your star fisherman,
山酿  掉入河中呢
Sam Niang, to the river?
孔恩瀑布是世界上
The Khone Falls have more water flowing over them
老挝  孔恩瀑布
北纬13°56'53''  东经105°56'26''
流量最大的瀑布
than any other waterfall in the world.
宽广的湄公河的一条狭道
A narrowing of the mighty Mekong river
困住了迁徙的鱼群
funnels the migrating fish
同时也提供了一个危险却有利可图的机会
and provides a dangerous, if lucrative, opportunity.
第一天
摄制组来此探索
The crew's here to capture the extreme lengths
当地人捕鱼的极限
that locals will go to catch fish.
山酿成为拍摄对象
Sam Niang is lucky.
他有办法到达他的小岛去捕鱼
He has access to his own small island for fishing.
但是要想到达目的地
But to get to his prime spot,
他必须冒生命危险
he must risk life and limb.
到了六月  开始进入雨季  我会很开心
在雨季里  人们不可能过河上岛
只有我可以用我的绳索走过去
那是我捕鱼的重要地点
如果有鱼
没有谁可以和我一起捕鱼
为了拍下山酿走高空绳索的奇观
To capture the spectacle of Sam Niang's high-wire feat,
第二天
摄制组采用了一个在电缆上滑动
the crew have chosen a gadget that runs on wires
且通过电动控制摄像机的小装备
and that controls the camera electronically,
它被称为移动摄影车
known as a cable dolly.
这是其中最令人激动且广受欢迎的点子
And the idea is, it's one of our most exciting and sought-after shots,
蕾妮・戈弗雷
人类星球研究员
这样我们就可以跟拍在绳索上行走的人了
so we can follow someone walking across the tightrope,
摄像机可以跟着他们移动
so the camera moves with them
并且将咆哮的激流展现在大家眼前
and then pulls out to reveal the angry water.
但是  要在一条如此狂怒的激流上
But rigging such a hi-tech system
安装这样的高端系统可不是件容易的活
over a raging torrent is no easy feat,
需要有专业的装配人员
and it requires a specialist rigger.
我们为摄影车装上电缆
We're just trying to get the cable across for the dolly,
蒂姆・福格
绳索技师
这位当地人只要
so the local guy's just
像他平常那样从绳索上走过去就行了
shimmied across the wires, as he does every day.
维尔斯特・蒂姆负责电缆
Whilst Tim works on the cables,
摄制组其他人
the rest of the team
则全神贯注于从各个角度拍摄急流
concentrate on filming the rapids from every other angle,
甚至不惜冒险置身其中
even shooting in the rapids themselves.
我刚刚到了那儿  不是很远
I'll just go here. It won't be a long run.
米克・奥谢
划艇运动员及安全顾问
这大概要花两到三分钟
It'll take two or three minutes.
米克・奥谢是第一个
Mick O'Shea was the first man ever to
横渡湄公河西藏到中国南部河段的人
navigate the entire Mekong, from Tibet to southern China-
他为我们捕捉到了更为真实的镜头
just the man to capture a fish-eye view.
即便是他  也不得不屈服于
But even he succumbs to
汹涌澎湃的湄公河
the full force of the Mekong in surge.
他的皮艇被猛烈的激流打入水中
His kayak is sucked under by the powerful current
顺流而下
and swept downstream.
经过几分钟的焦急等待
After a few worrying minutes,
米克出现了  他重新掌控了划艇
Mick re-appears, back in control,
虽安然无恙却心有余悸
safe but shaken.
第三天
对湄公河的威慑力有了更深的认识后
With new-found respect for the Mekong's power,
摄制组回到了陆地进行拍摄
the crew stick to solid ground.
他们通过一个四米长的摇臂
Using a four-metre jib,
跟拍山酿在一块
they follow Sam Niang as he negotiates
极为危险的岩石上撒网捕鱼的场景
a treacherous rocky outcrop to cast his net.
第四天
下来点儿  继续  很好
Over and down, OK? And on... Good.
现在  蒂姆已经为移动摄影车搭好了电缆
By now, Tim has the rigging ready for the dolly.
你要这个东西吗
Do you want this up here?
有一团巨大的乌云飘过来了
There's a massive cloud come over.
但是还没来得及把机器遮好  就下雨了
But no sooner than it's in place, the heavens open.
这是他们最不想看到的事
It's the last thing they need.
拍摄因为技术和安全原因暂停了
Dolly filming stops for technical and safety reasons.
狂风暴雨之下
走在绳索上令我有些害怕
我怕掉进水里
如果掉进了水里  就必死无疑了
马克・福劳斯
人类星球制片人
现在雨下得不大
There's just a little spot of rain.
我看就快停了
I think rain's stopping play!
我们的发电机罢工了
我们打算下载剪辑  以继续明天的拍摄
但是雨水可能会毁了电脑和相机
不知道接下来会怎样
-没关系  电子产品的防水性能很好  -没错
-Yeah...Cos electronics survive the rain well. - Yeah.
第二天早上  如担心的一样
The next morning, it's clear that, as feared,
雨水渗进了电子设备
water has got into the electronics.
第五天
那现在是什么问题呢
So what's gone wrong with it now?
最主要的是移动摄像机没有马达
这样就不能让它在电缆上来回移动
我们现在打算用一个平衡锤来拉它
这个方法已经用了很多年了
这么说现代化科技还是被老式方法取代了
So the new, modern technology is ousted by the old-school way.
完全正确
第六天
我现在爬上去
I'm going to go up there now
把摄像机装上
and, um, put the camera on!
理查德・柯比
摄影师
我的天  好吧
Oh, my... Whoa! OK.
摄制组最终使移动摄影车正常运转了
The crew finally get the cable dolly working,
现在是时候开工了
so now it's time to get creative.
灯光  移动摄影车  安全组
The light, the dolly, the safety team
和最为重要的山酿
and most importantly, Sam Niang,
大家都要齐心协力
all have to work in unison.
开始
Go!
位置不对
We turned it the wrong way.
好了  蒂姆
OK, Tim.
不行
No.
差不多  差不多了
Nearly, nearly.
重新来  好的
Bring it all back, yes.
开始
Go.
不行  还是不行
No. Still no!
但山酿还是很开心 不是吗
Sam Niang looks really happy, though, doesn't he?
每当他从绳索上走过去
My heart's in my mouth every time
我都会紧张万分
he has to go over that rope.
你很开心  我可是很担心
You look really happy, and I'm really worried!
阳光穿破云层的阻隔
The sun breaks through the clouds,
最终光芒万丈
and finally it all comes together.
太棒了 我们成功了
Yay, we've got a keeper!
太棒了
That's great!
非常感谢你
Thanks very much, you.
总算可以松一口气了
What a relief.
尽管遇到了重重阻挠
Despite the odds,
人类星球摄制组最终还是取得了胜利
the Human Planet team have triumphed.
第七集 完